A Guide to the Wickham Family Papers, 1754-1977
Virginia Historical Society
Records of rental properties in Richmond managed by Charles A. Rose Co. (225 North Boulevard, 721 West Broad Street, 1333 West Broad Street, and 2711 Hanover Avenue) and by Elam and Funsten (1309 East Cary Street, 13 North Governor Street) appear in folders 5-6. Lastly, estate miscellany is comprised of correspondence and an application for widow's benefits filed with the Railroad Retirement Board, 1947; and an agreement with Hill Carter concerning timber on "Loblolly Hill," in Hanover County, a portion of the Wickham farm.
Series 8 concerns Elise Warwick Barksdale (1861-1952), who married Herny Taylor Wickham in 1885 and lived at "Hickory Hill." Her correspondence includes one letter to her father dated 1869, and numerous items of communication with family members, 1896-1948. Some are written or received as a member of the Board of Managers or as president of the Exchange for Woman's Work in Richmond, Va. Many letters are written by George Barksdale Wickham (while attending Virginia Military Institute, Lexington) and Williams Carter Wickham ([1887-1985] while serving in the U.S. Navy), while a letter from Doctor George Ainsley Barksdale itself bears a letter of Margaret (Branch) Glasgow written at Summer Rest resort in Greenwood, VA.
Financial records (boxes 41-42) consist of loose accounts (including numerous canceled checks), 1902-1936, three passbooks on Richmond banks, 1891-1919, and seven check stub books, 1896-1923. Bank statements and canceled checks from 1948-1950 are filed separately. State and federal income and personal property tax forms and returns, 1941-1951, follow.
Farm records at "Hickory Hill" are quite similar to those kept by Henry Taylor Wickham and consist of time sheets, payrolls, produce statements, records of expenditures, and loose accounts arranged by year. Records (including some lease agreements) of investment properties in Richmond managed for Mrs. Wickham by Charles A. Rose Co. in the years 1932, 1942-1945, and 1947-1950, cover income and disbursements for rental properties at 1517-21 West Broad Street, 613-15 North Lombardy Street, 721-23 West Broad Street, 225 North Boulevard, 1319-23 West Broad Street, 1333 West Broad Street, and 2711 Hanover Avenue. Those managed by Elam and Funsten were located at 1309 East Cary Street, 13 North Governor Street, 1417-23 East Cary street, 1301 East Main Street, and 124-30 Virginia Street. Morton G. Thalhimer, Inc., managed the properties at 1319 West Broad Street in 1932 and in 1947-1950.Box 47 contains some miscellaneous items of members of the Barksdale and Warwick families. Mrs. Wickham's ancestors. An account, 1859, of Abraham Warwick with Hunt and Roskell of London bears a draft of a letter of Warwick to that firm, dated 19 November 1860, concerning the unsettled political situation in the American South. A letter of Robert E. Lee, dated 1 June 1866, to Elise Florence (Warwick) Barksdale has been indexed elsewhere. These miscellaneous items also include passports, 1810 and 1854, issued to William Jones Barksdale by William Pinkney (as American minister to great Britain) and William Learned Marcy (as U.S. secretary of state). Newspaper clippings collected by Doctor George Ainsley Barksdale primarily concern Virginia and Confederate military history, while the doctor's scrapbook, 1889-1892, includes a pardon signed by Andrew Johnson and William Henry Seward (p. 15), as well as autograph notes (taken from official C.S.A. documents) of Fitzhugh Lee, John Letcher, James Alexander Seddon, Walter Herron Taylor, and John Withers (p. 92). The scrapbook if filed oversize after Box 47.
Box 48 contains records of the distribution of land at "Brookfield," Henrico County, VA., to the heirs of Abraham (or Abram) Warwick, including a portion of adjoining land that was developed in 1925 as "Lakeside Terrace." Materials include bills of complaint, answers, proceedings, decrees, memoranda, plats, leases, deeds, and notes and correspondence of Henry Taylor Wickham in the related cases of Eliza Agnes (Hayes) Warwick (widow of Abram Warwick v. Peter C. Warwick etal. and Caroline Warwick v. Elise Warwick (Barksdale) Wickham etal.
Mrs. Wickham kept records as an officer of the Ladies' Aid Society of St. Paul's Episcopal Church in Hanover County from 1893 to 1916. The organization raised funds for building projects, mission activities, and to supplement the salary of their rector. These records are a few items of correspondence; an account book, 1893, which includes lists of members; a bank pass book, 1893-1894; loose accounts; resolutions of the vestry; and notes.
A visitors'' register, 1930-1961, records the sojourn of guests at "Hickory Hill" and includes the signatures of Admiral William Fredericks Halsey (25 Sept. 1938, 29 July 1942, 14 Nov. 1946, 27 Jan. 1950, and 22 April 1950) and William Munford Tuck (15 April 1939). Mrs. Wickham made many diary-like entries in this volume through these years. Another visitors' register, 1949, was kept on behalf of the Ashland Branch of the Garden Club of Virginia. Miscellany includes a membership certificate, 1896, in the Virginia Society of the Colonial Dames of America; a life membership certificate issued in 1909 by the Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities; newspaper clippings concerning the Wickham and Barksdale families and "Hickory Hill"; and notes, recipes and lines of verse. Letters, cards and telegrams of condolence sent to Williams Carter Wickham on his mother's death in 1952 complete Box 48.
Series 9 contains materials relating to Henry Taylor Wickham's brother, William Fanning Wickham (1860-1900), who trained to be an attorney and lived for many years at "Hickory Hill." His records surviving in this collection include materials concerning the Hanover Troop (Troop D of the 1st Cavalry Battalion of Virginia Volunteers) consisting of letters (including one from Governor Fitzhugh Lee, 19 July) written to Wickham in 1889, many enclosing bills of lading for military supplies; and oaths of allegiance subscribed to by officers and men of the unit. Wickham's personal miscellany includes two items of correspondence, 1874; loose accounts, 1877 and 1889; notes and records concerning "Hickory Hill" farm, 1886-1888; and materials, 1900, concerning his estate.
Henry and William Wickham's sister, Ann Carter (Wickham) Renshaw Byerly appears throughout the collection, but in Series 10 are gathered only a small number of letters, 1869-1888, written to her by Eleanor Agnes Lee, Mary Anna Randolph (Custis) Lee, and William Henry Fitzhugh Lee.
Series 11 contains the papers of Williams Carter Wickham (1887-1985), son of Henry Taylor and Elise Wickham and the last major character to appear in this collection. He attended the U.S. Naval Academy in Annapolis, Md., and served for many years in the U.S. Navy. During the Second World War he was hospitalized in Denver, Colo., and later Bethesda, Md., and retired on disability in 1945 after reaching the rank of captain.
Captain Wickham's correspondence, 1897-1967, includes communications from Harry Flood Byrd, Richmond attorney Randolph Grayson Dashiell, Admiral William Frederick Halsey, and Wickham's wife, Credilla (Miller) Wickham. Records of his naval service consist of a letter (copy), 1940, of Doctor George Ben Johnston concerning Wickham's physical condition; grade records, 1907, and certificates of graduation, 1909, 1911, from the U.S. Naval Academy; commissions (some signed by Claude Augustus Swanson, William Howard Taft and Woodrow Wilson); a Bachelor of Science degree awarded as a graduate of the Naval Academy in 1938; orders and reports concerning Wickham's naval service, 1941-1943; correspondence and records concerning his disability and retirement, 1944-1949 (including orders signed by James Forrestal); correspondence and records concerning military insurance with the Veterans Administration; commendation for services, 1942-1944, as Convoy Control Officer of the U.S. Tenth Fleet; and an address, n.d., of Wickham to the Hanover County Woman's Club concerning his early years of naval service.Miscellany is comprised of an undated teacher's recommendation signed by E. R. Whitlocke; correspondence and exams of Wickham in the LaSalle Extension University course in law, Chicago, Ill., 1945; lineage charts showing the descent of Williams Carter Wickham for the Virginia Society of Colonial Dames; wedding invitations; a membership certificate, 1912, in the A.P.V.A.; and collected newspaper clippings.
Captain Wickham's younger brother, George Barksdale Wickham (1888-1928), attended Virginia Military Institute and later became a Richmond businessman. His records, in Series 12 of this collection, include school materials, n.d.-1903; grade reports while a student at V.M.I., 1904-1905, 1907; a wedding invitation, 1916; A.P.V.A. certificate, 1912; and obituary notices.
In Series 13, the collection closes with family miscellany (materials of Lawrence Vernon Miller Wickham while service in the U.S. Marine Corps; and a commonplace book, 1973-1977, of Lois (Wingfield) Wickham, widow of Williams Carter Wickham [1917-1982]) and a few items of general miscellany (autograph album, 1877-1889, kept by Carrie Lee Colton in Annapolis and Jessup's Cut, Md.; and correspondence, 1877-1886, of Reverend Pike Powers of Richmond, Va.)
Arrangement
Arranged in thirteen series by main entry and further subdivided by date or subject as necessary.
Index Terms
Agriculture -- Virginia -- History.; Carter, Charles, 1818-; Chesapeake and Ohio Railway Company.; Democratic Party (Va.) -- History -- 20th century.; Diaries -- Virginia -- Hanover County -- History -- 19th century.; Fanning family.; Fugitive slaves -- Virginia -- Hanover County -- History -- 19th century.; Gist, Samuel, d. 1815.; Hanover County (Va.) -- History.; Hickory Hill (Hanover County, Va.); Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870.; Lee, William Henry Fitzhugh, 1837-1891.; North Wales (Caroline County, Va.); Plantations -- Virginia -- Hanover County.; Real estate management -- Virginia -- Richmond -- History -- 20th century.; Reconstruction -- Virginia.; Republican Party (Va.) -- History -- 19th century.; Slaves -- Emancipation -- Virginia.; Trusts and trustees -- Virginia -- History -- 19th century.; Virginia -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; Virginia -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950.; Wickham, Elise Warwick Barksdale, 1861-1952.; Wickham family.; Wickham, Henry Taylor, 1849-1943.; Wickham, John, 1763-1839.; Wickham, Lucy Penn Taylor, 1830-1913.; Wickham, William Carter, 1820-1888.; Wickham, William Fanning, 1793-1880.
Contents List
- Series 1. William Fanning (1728-1782), Greensville County, Va. (Box 1)
  Certificate of ordination; letter, 1781; will, 1782; genealogical notes; Henry Taylor Wickham correspondence, 1930
- William Fanning (1728-1782), Greensville County, Va. (Box 1)
- Edmund Fanning (1739-1818), Nova Scotia, Canada (Box 1 (cont.))
  Correspondence, 1783-1812; letters, 1777-1778; prayer; biographical sketches
- John Wickham (1763-1839), Richmond, Va.
  - Correspondence, 1778-1799 (Box 1 (cont.))
    Includes letters to David Parish
  - Land records and miscellany (Box 1 (cont.))
  - Estate materials (Box 2-4)
    Wills; correspondence; financial and land records; Wickham et al. v. Leigh et al.; W.H.F. Lee trust
- William Fanning Wickham (1793-1880), "Hickory Hill," Hanover County, Va.
  - Diaries, 1828-1880 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1817-1878 (Box 6)
    Includes letters of condolence, 1868
  - Financial and legal materials (Box 7)
    Accounts; memorandum of stocks; bonds; land records ("Hickory Hill," "South Wales," "The Lane").
  - Samuel Gist estate (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous materials (Box 9-10)
    Frances (Wickham) Graham trust; pardon materials; genealogical notes; commonplace book, miscellany; estate
- Williams Carter Wickham (1820-1888), "Hickory Hill," Hanover County, Va.
  - Letterbooks, 1877-1881 (Box 10 (cont.))
  - Correspondence, 1862-1888 (Box 11)
  - Financial materials, 1861-1888 (Box 12-13)
    Personal account books, 1875-1885 (11 v.); account book, 1880-1888, "household expenses"; accounts, 1861, 1868-1888; bonds, 1877-1888
  - Hickory Hill materials, 1866-1888 (Box 13 (cont.)-15)
    Farm books, 1866-1888 (15 v.); loose materials, 1871-1888
  - North Wales materials, 1867-1887 (Box 16)
  - Margaret William Tryon (Fanning) Cumberland estate materials, 1880-1888. (Box 17)
  - Frances (Wickham) Graham trust, 1880-1888 (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous and Other legal papers, 1872-1888 (Box 19)
    George Harrison Byrd trust; Julia Leiper (Taylor) Hubard trust; C. and O. Railway materials, 1872-1888; Republican party materials, ca. 1881-1887; miscellaneous land records; general miscellany, estate.
- Lucy Penn (Taylor) Wickham (1830-1913), "Hickory Hill," Hanover County, Va.
  - Correspondence, 1848-1913. (Box 20)
  - Financial materials, 1875-1913 (Box 20 (cont.))
    Accounts, 1875-1913; tax returns; Chesapeake Land and Improvement Co..
  - Miscellaneous (Box 20 (cont.))
    Genealogical notes; estate of Henry Taylor
  - Estate materials, 1913-1915 (Box 20 (cont.)-21)
- Henry Taylor Wickham (1849-1943), "Hickory Hill," Hanover County, Va.
  - Letterbooks, 1931-1940 (Box 22-23)
  - Correspondence, 1874-1940 (Box 24-25)
  - Financial materials, 1867-1942 (Box 25)
    Account book, 1867-1870; account book, 1942; passbooks, 1915-1926 (2 v.); check stub book, 1922-1926; and accounts, 1920-1925, 1931-1933, 1938-1939.
  - Richmond, Va., rental properties. (Box 26)
  - Hickory Hill materials (Box 27-30)
    Farm books, 1893-1913 [4 v.]; time sheets, payrolls, produce statements; and land records.
  - Student records, etc., 1867-1935. (Box 30 (cont.))
  - Virginia State materials (Box 30 (cont.)-31)
    Speeches, addresses, etc.
  - Scrapbooks, 1874-1943 (Box 32-37)
  - Legal papers (Box 37 (cont.))
    Law practice; land and tax records
  - Miscellany (Box 37 (cont.)-38)
    Newspaper clippings; genealogical notes and records; general miscellany.
  - Estate materials, 1943-1945 (Box 38 (cont.)-39)
- Elise Warwick (Barksdale) Wickham (1861-1952), "Hickory Hill," Hanover County, Va.
  - Correspondence, 1869, 1896-1948 (Box 40)
  - Financial materials, 1891-1951 (Box 41-42)
    Accounts, 1902-1936; passbooks (3 v.), 1891-1919; check stub books (7 v.,) 1896-1923; bank statements and canceled checks, 1948-1950; tax forms and returns, 1941-1951.
  - Hickory Hill materials. Farm records (time sheets, payrolls, produce statements, accounts, etc.) (Box 43-45)
  - Richmond, Va., rental properties, 1931-1951. (Box 45 (cont.)-47)
  - Barksdale and Warwick family miscellany. (Box 47 (cont.))
  - Miscellaneous materials. (Box 48)
    "Brookfield," Henrico County, Va., materials, 1891-1925; Ladies' Aid Society, St. Paul's Episcopal Church, Hanover County, Va.; visitor's registers (2 v.), 1930-1961; miscellany
- William Fanning Wickham (1860-1900), "Hickory Hill," Hanover County, Va. (Box 49)
  Hanover Troop materials, 1889; personal miscellany.
- Ann Carter (Wickham) Renshaw Byerly (1851-1939), "Hickory Hill," Hanover County, Va. (Box 49 (cont.))
  Letters, 1869-1888.
- Williams Carter Wickham (1887-1985), Washington, D. C. and "Hickory Hill," Hanover County, Va.
  - Correspondence, 1897-1967. (Box 49 (cont.)-50)
  - U.S. Navy Service and miscellany, 1904-1949. (Box 51)
- George Barksdale Wickham (1888-1928), Richmond, Va. (Box 51 (cont.))
  School materials and miscellany.
- Miscellany. (Box 51 (cont.))
  Family and general miscellany.